<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Richard's Log</title><link>http://richard.kellnerovci.sk/</link><description>Public notepad about stuff I am currently playing with...</description><atom:link href="http://richard.kellnerovci.sk/feeds/conference.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 21:26:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Open source weekend in Bratislava</title><link>http://richard.kellnerovci.sk/opensource-weekend-in-bratilsava-2015.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;During the weekend 14-15th of March 2015, &lt;a href="http://www.soit.sk/"&gt;SOIT&lt;/a&gt; was organising Open Source weekend in Bratislava. As a member I have decided to gave a talk how to start Django project. Here is my brief summary of the conference and what it was all about. I think I can separate talks into several sections, even these were not official sections of the conference. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenData and Open government was one large section in Saturday afternoon. Even thou I am not working with big data, I have always supported the idea that all data produced by any government should be open and easily accessible by people. Now I have realised how important it is. There have to be people who understand the topic, because otherwise it would be just another project that looks good on paper, but is useless in real world. We have several bright people trying to push government right way, so new interesting projects can be born, instead of wasting money on useless webpages produced by half professional companies. Unfortunately public interest seems to be very low for this topic. Part of this section was talk about secret service attempt for a new law invading peoples privacy, followed by nice discussion. I have to mention there is a &lt;a href="http://www.changenet.sk/?section=kampane&amp;amp;x=796541"&gt;petition&lt;/a&gt; against this law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Conference was attended by quite a lot of people from RedHat, which is based in Brno, not far away from Bratislava. There was plenty of Fedora DVDs so I decided to switch from Mint, as the live DVD was working fine for me and drivers I had problems with in the past seems to be resolved. There was a large variety of talks from general explanations how Fedora workstation is done to Linux core interruptions. It was rather nice and refreshing as I was using Fedora long years in my previous job and I can see they are trying hard to keep good operating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably the largest part was dedicated to introduce the open source projects. Part of the speakers were introducing their own projects to larger audience and the others talked how to start using tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me this was the most interesting bit. I have learned few new tricks and I decided to start using &lt;a href="http://www.ansible.com/"&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt; as it seems cool tool for my horde of Raspberry Pi’s. I gave a talk about &lt;a href="https://github.com/ricco386/zaciname-s-djangom"&gt;how to start with Django&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://richard.kellnerovci.sk/zaciname-s-djangom/#/"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;). It was brief introduction to Django and quick tutorial how to start a project with explanation of models, views, templates with examples of Don’t Repeat Yourself principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I think the event went rather well, and next year I will gladly join the conference again. Apart glitch with buffet closed on Sunday, everything went fine and I am happy I met several interesting people.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Richard Kellner</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 21:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:richard.kellnerovci.sk,2015-04-10:opensource-weekend-in-bratilsava-2015.html</guid><category>Conference</category></item><item><title>PHPNW 2012</title><link>http://richard.kellnerovci.sk/phpnw-2012.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have been lucky and during the weekend I attended PHPNW 2012 in Manchester. I would like to express my feelings and shortly describe what it was about. Conference has started on Friday with workshops and probably most interesting was Rob Allen and Evan Coury with: Building a Zend Framework 2 Application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday morning official part was opened by Ade Oshineye with Developer Experience, API Design and Craft Skills. He explained how he had worked on Google Maps API and what should developers think about when designing APIs. During the day I have checked several speeches, and I will mention at two of them. Effective Code Reviews, by Sebastian Marek, how to automate tasks before we start to review code after other developers and what to focus on so this review has meaning. At the end Ian Barber from Google spoke how to manage large amount of data from live stream in speech Building a Firehose. After all speeches there was short word by sponsors and we all went for a beer, to have a technical and less technical discussions…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday was shorter, but still very interesting. John Cleveley was speaking how did they create a responsive page for BBC and for the rest of the day I have decided to learn theories, I went to listen to Harrie Verveer how to Recognizing Smelly Code. And at the end I watched The Art of Application Logging, by Ben Waine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Appart from news that happened in PHP world lectures were more or less advanced. Therefore I think conference was addition and I can recommend next year to any PHP programmer. At the end I will just mention that all speeches were recorded, so hopefully they will be available on &lt;a href="http://conference.phpnw.org.uk/phpnw12/" title="PHPNW 2012"&gt;official page&lt;/a&gt; soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Richard Kellner</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 15:12:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:richard.kellnerovci.sk,2012-10-08:phpnw-2012.html</guid><category>PHP</category><category>Conference</category></item></channel></rss>