<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Richard's Log</title><link>http://richard.kellnerovci.sk/</link><description>Public notepad about stuff I am currently playing with...</description><atom:link href="http://richard.kellnerovci.sk/feeds/php.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 15:12:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>PHPNW 2012</title><link>http://richard.kellnerovci.sk/phpnw-2012.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have been lucky and during the weekend I attended PHPNW 2012 in Manchester. I would like to express my feelings and shortly describe what it was about. Conference has started on Friday with workshops and probably most interesting was Rob Allen and Evan Coury with: Building a Zend Framework 2 Application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday morning official part was opened by Ade Oshineye with Developer Experience, API Design and Craft Skills. He explained how he had worked on Google Maps API and what should developers think about when designing APIs. During the day I have checked several speeches, and I will mention at two of them. Effective Code Reviews, by Sebastian Marek, how to automate tasks before we start to review code after other developers and what to focus on so this review has meaning. At the end Ian Barber from Google spoke how to manage large amount of data from live stream in speech Building a Firehose. After all speeches there was short word by sponsors and we all went for a beer, to have a technical and less technical discussions…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday was shorter, but still very interesting. John Cleveley was speaking how did they create a responsive page for BBC and for the rest of the day I have decided to learn theories, I went to listen to Harrie Verveer how to Recognizing Smelly Code. And at the end I watched The Art of Application Logging, by Ben Waine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Appart from news that happened in PHP world lectures were more or less advanced. Therefore I think conference was addition and I can recommend next year to any PHP programmer. At the end I will just mention that all speeches were recorded, so hopefully they will be available on &lt;a href="http://conference.phpnw.org.uk/phpnw12/" title="PHPNW 2012"&gt;official page&lt;/a&gt; soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Richard Kellner</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 15:12:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:richard.kellnerovci.sk,2012-10-08:phpnw-2012.html</guid><category>PHP</category><category>Conference</category></item></channel></rss>